Friends, if you are investing in NPS,
whether you are a government employee or a
private employee, or even if you are
investing in MPS on your own, then
here is how you can increase the corpus in NPS,
how you can get higher returns.
In this video, I am showing you proper information with a demo,
so you must watch this video completely, it is a
very useful video for you.
Before moving ahead in the video, let me
introduce myself to you.
My name is Brijendra Gautam and you are watching
ABTech Financial Advisor. For the last three
years, I have been working in the field of insurance and mutual funds.
If you have
any query or want to do SIP in mutual funds,
then you can contact us.
Let's move ahead in the video and
talk about NPS.
So, you all know that
NPS is compulsory for all the government employees.
NPS was started in 2004 and today,
NPS is deducted for all the employees of the country who were appointed after 2004.
In this, whatever your salary is made by combining your basic and dearness allowance,
your money is deducted at 10% and the
government contributes at 14%, so
10% of your salary and 14% of the government's,
this entire amount is deposited in your NPS account,
okay, now the money that is going,
okay, so how can you track where it is going,
for this there is an NPS
application, from there you
can see how much money has been deducted, how much
money has been earned, how much return are you getting,
you can see all the things there,
okay, I will explain in this video, right now, in this
money that has gone, if you have
seen the return or not, then you will see that
in this your return would be around 75% or 8%
or 85%, it will
not be more than this or it will be maximum 9% also, so
why is the return coming so low, if
you want to increase it, then how can you increase it,
see here, all the government schemes,
all the government employees'
money that goes to NPS, where is it
invested  So
your money is invested in Government Bonds. What are Government Bonds? Let me
tell you that
when the government borrows money for any of its development work,
right? From where does it take it? It
takes it from a pension fund manager.
Many pension fund managers in India
like LIC, UTI, SBI borrow money from them
and pay them interest at the rate of around 9% or 10%. So
what happens in return for the interest? When the government borrows money, they
issue a bond saying
that we need this much money and you will get this much
return in it. So, our pension
money is
invested in Government Bonds in a way. What
happens in this? There is no risk in this. The
government is taking your money, so the
risk in it is negligible. It is not at all
safe money, but the return
you get here is also less,
around 0%. So, if you want to get a higher return in this, then
apart from Government Bonds, there are three more schemes and three more assets
where you can invest your money if you want.
For that, you have to go to the bank and  You just
need to make one setting, nothing else. If
you're okay, first understand which three schemes there are. The
first is Government Bonds. The
second is Corporate Bonds.
What happens in Corporate Bonds? You get a slightly higher return than
Government Bonds. And
here too, it's considered almost safe. There's
no risk, but
you'll get more money here than Government Bonds.
Apart from this, there's
equity. Equity simply means, if you understand the
share market, if you invest in equity,
your returns will be
very high. It will be around 14-15 percent.
If you look at the returns of the last 10 years,
which are our pension funds, then their
returns have been around 14 to 145 percent. There are
many websites where you
can check the performance of your NPS. If you want to get
higher returns, then you will have to
invest in equity. And let me
tell you the fourth option, there are some alternate schemes. If you
want,
you can invest in alternate asset classes there too. Equity wo
n't give you very high returns there.  You will
get less from this but if you want,
you can invest there also. So if
you want to get higher returns, then you will have to
invest in equity. What will you have to do for that?
How will it be possible? Now
understand this. First of all, you have to
go to the NPS website and register here.
If you have not done this till now, okay? If
you already have the NPS app, then
download the NPS app and
log in to it. If you do
not know the password, you will
get the option of forget password. Forget password will come there.
OTP will come on your mobile.
You can create a new password through OTP.
Look, this is your NPS application
whose name is NPS by Protean and
NSDL e-Government will be written here. Here,
open is written here. Click on open. In
this way, the app will open. Now look here,
you will see the login option. If you
have an PRAN number and password, then
you will go to login. Here, you have to enter your PRAN
number at the top and the password below
and from here, you have to login. Now
click on OK here. Now see,
go to equity.  For this or to change your fund manager,
understand carefully what you have to do,
look at the left side, three lines are visible,
you have to click here, you will see the
option see scheme change, here
you have to click on scheme change, in
this way see here the option will come, the option will
open, the meaning of this pop up is
written here, whatever change you make will take at
least 1+1 day to happen, that
means it will take at least four working
days, you click on proceed,
now see, wherever your money will be going,
it will be written here, see
here it is written in mine
ICICI Prudential Pension Fund Scheme
Tier 1 and see here the
allocation is already there, okay, so I have
changed it, but if you have
not changed it, then by default here your
LIC
SBI and your UTI, these three
options will be written here, okay, so
you will see that by default only that will come, I have
changed it here, in this way it is
coming here, okay, so here  Now
look below it is written change, now I have
changed it once, so look here it is
written scheme change one and
PFM change one, I have changed the scheme as well
and PFM means pension
fund manager, I have changed that too,
you can change the pension fund manager once a year
and you
can change the scheme twice a year, which is written here above,
so here now we will go to change,
see here you will see three options,
first is standard, second is active
and third is auto by default, all of them will be
set to standard here, if it is set to standard then
here it means that in the
three schemes that are shown here,
you will be shown LIC, SBI and UTI here
and whatever money is there here goes
into government bonds, it is
very simple to see government bonds, if you look here then
it will be written G, G
means government bonds, okay, here if
you go to active choice, if you
go to active choice then you will have to choose the pension fund
manager here because I can
change only once  I have already done so that's why my
ICICI will show you the rest of the entire
list will open up for you, okay so here you will
select it Pension Fund Manager and
after this you will have to choose the asset class,
see asset class, G is written here
ICICI Prudential Pension Fund Scheme,
G G means Government Bond, so
if you go under Active Choice then
here you will get to invest only in Government Bond, there is
no benefit, we want to choose equity,
here you will have to go to Auto Choice, okay
when you select Auto here then
you will see two schemes, look carefully
Moderate Auto Choice LC 50 and
Conservative Auto Choice AC
25, what does this mean, it means
if we go to Moderate Auto Choice LC
50, in this 50% of your money will go to equity,
30% of your money will go to Corporate Bond
and 20% will go to Government Bond, but
if you see my
scheme here then look carefully, it is written in all of them,
see in the top one  It is written
here carefully, it is written
ICICI Prudential Pension Fund Scheme E
and look here it is written allocation % E
means equity at 50,
here look Scheme G is written, G
means government bond and
look here it is %, after this look here see Scheme
CC means corporate bond and here the
allocation is 30, okay, so if you
choose LC 50 here, then
your allocation will be done in the same way here
and this allocation will keep decreasing according to your age, that is, the
portion of equity will keep decreasing
and the proportion in government bond and corporate
bond will keep increasing as
your age increases, so
your allocation here will be according to your age,
so if you
want to choose LC 50, then you can choose LC 50 here,
if you do not want to take much risk,
your age is around 40, 45 or 50,
then you can choose LC 25 here.  Here,
only 25% of your money will go into equity, the
rest will go into government bonds and
corporate bonds. In this way,
you will have to choose one. If your A is up to 30 or 35 years,
then you can choose moderate LC 50.
If LC 75 is showing you, then you
can also choose LC 75 because in LC 75,
your money will go into equity at 75. Okay, so
suppose you have selected LC 50. Now here it is
asking to select pension fund manager.
So, in mine, only one pension fund manager is being shown
because we can choose this pension fund manager only once a year.
Secondly,
when the session is over, that is, one year will be over,
after that you can choose another fund manager.
I have changed it to recent, due to which only
ICICI will be shown. Rest of the time,
you will see many pension fund
managers here. In this, you will also have LIC,
SBI, UTI, Aditya
Birla, HDFC, Tata,
so you can choose the fund manager as per your choice.
Okay, do
your research and see if it suits you.
Which is the best fund and you choose it for yourself
and accordingly you will do it from here,
select it, okay, after this you will
submit it here, like when you click on submit, it will
ask for confirmation here, okay, you
click on confirmation, you will get an
OTP, you enter the OTP, after that
you will get an acknowledgement number and
after that your
pension fund
manager will be changed here, so in this way you can change your pension fund
manager, you can
change the pension fund manager once a year and if you want to
change the eight class, you can
change it twice a year, so I hope
you liked the video, if you have any query or
doubt, then you must ask in the comment box, I will
say this much,
if you have not subscribed to the channel, then do
subscribe to the channel, thank you very much